Register of the Ernest Lundeen Papers, 1860-1944
Hoover Institution Archives
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1892-1940.
  - "The Farmer Labor Party in 1933," 1933 May 26. Speech, U.S. Congress. Printed copy (Folder 6)
  - Remarks against adjournment, U.S. Congress, 1933 June 10. Typescript (Folder 7)
  - "The March of the Morgan Millions," 1933 June 13. Speech, U.S. Congress. Holograph and printed copy (Folder 8)
  - "Big Business vs the Veteran," Foreign Service, 1933 Dec. Reprint (Folder 9)
  - "Repeal the Economy Act - Make America Safe for Veterans," 1933 June 15. Speech, U.S. Congress. Printed copy, correspondence, clippings (Folder 10)
  - Radio talk on veterans legislation, KSTP, 1933 Dec. 21. Typescript (Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous, 1934. Correspondence, printed copies of remarks, clippings (Folder 12)
  - "Our American Constitution Recognizes Emergencies," 1934 Jan. 10. Speech, U.S. Congress. Background material, printed copy, clippings (Box 374., Folder 1)
  - "America - What of the Future?" 1934 July 13. Speech, U.S. Congress. Typescript draft (Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1935. Correspondence, background material, typescript drafts (Folder 3)
  - "Highlights of the 74th Congress, 1st Session," The State News, 1935. Typescript and correspondence (Folder 4)
  - Radio talks on administration events in Washington, 1935 Jan. -Aug. Typescript copies (Folder 5)
  - Radio talk on social insurance, WDGY, Minneapolis, Minnesota, 1935 Jan. 20. Typescript, clippings (Folder 6)
  - Speech on U.S. - U.S.S.R. relations, New York City, New York, 1935 Feb. 25. Three typescript drafts, correspondence, clippings (Folder 7)
  - Speech, Friends of the Soviet Union, Milwaukee, Wisconsin, 1935 Mar. 30. Two typescript copies (Folder 8)
  - "Workers Unemployment, Old Age, and Social Insurance Bill," 1935 April 3. Speech, U.S. Congress. Typescript draft, proofs, printed copy (Folder 9)
  - "Social Security Necessary to Life, Liberty, and Pursuit of Happiness," 1935 April 18. Speech, U.S. Congress. Printed copy (Folder 10)
  - "Administration Social 'Insecurity' Bill Makes Necessary United Front National Labor Party.. .," 1935 April 19. Speech, U.S. Congress. Typescript draft and printed copy (Folder 11)
  - Speech, Columbia Broadcasting System and Cosmos Club, 1935 April 27. Typescript (Folder 12)
  - "Old Folks at Home," Plain Talk, 1935 May. Printed copy and correspondence (Folder 13)
  - "Federal Aid to Meet the Emergency in Education," 1935 May 16. Speech, U.S. Congress. Printed copy and correspondence (Folder 14)
  - "A Farmer Labor Party for the Nation," Common Sense, 1935 June. Typescript draft, printed copy, correspondence (Box 375., Folder 1)
  - "Four Thousand Fighting Planes, the Cost of One Battleship... Department of the Air Service," 1935 June 7. Speech, U.S. Congress. Printed copy, correspondence, clippings (Folder 2)
  - "A Congressional Record Digest... Digest and Index Plan Practical," 1935 June 21. Speech, U.S. Congress. Typescript draft, printed copy, correspondence (Folder 3)
  - "Charles A. Lindberg - Patriot, Pioneer, Statesman, Lawyer, Writer, Courageous Champion for the People," 1935 June 24. Speech, U.S. Congress. Proof copy, printed copy, correspondence (Folder 4)
  - "Sources of Wealth," 1935 Aug. 2. Speech, U.S. Congress. Proof copy, correspondence (Folder 5)
  - "Retrenchment, Retrogression, and Ruin - The Three R's of 'Economized' Education, 1935 Aug. 7. Speech, U.S. Congress. Typescript draft, printed copy, correspondence (Folder 6)
  - "The Great American Massacre," 1935 Aug. 17. Speech, U.S. Congress. Two printed copies, background materials, pamphlets, correspondence, clippings (Folder 7)
  - "A National Labor Party - Eventually, Why Not Now?" 1935 Aug. 17. Speech, U.S. Congress. Typescript, correspondence, clippings (Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous remarks, statements, 1936. Typescript drafts, correspondence, clippings, invitations (Box 376., Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1936. Mrs. Lundeen's correspondence, typescript speech drafts, background material (Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous notes and background material, 1936
    - General (Folder 3)
    - Bonus bill (Folder 4)
    - Constitutional reform (Folder 5)
    - Neutrality (Folder 6)
    - Postage rates (Folder 7)
    - Rural electrification (Folder 8)
    - Sob stories (Folder 9)
    - Unemployment (Folder 10)
    - Wealth and income (Box 377., Folder 1)
    - Youth (Folder 2)
  - "Social Security," 1936 Jan. 18. Speech, The People's Lobby. Printed copy and correspondence (Folder 3)
  - "Social Security - The Frazier-Lundeen Bill," 1936 Jan. 24. Speech, U.S. Congress. Printed copy, clippings (Folder 4)
  - "Social Security," 1936 Feb. Radio broadcast. Typescript notes, correspondence (Folder 5)
  - "Zeppelins for America," 1936 Feb. 11. Speech, U.S. Congress. Printed copy and background material (Folder 6)
  - "Susan B. Anthony - (and) Heroic Pioneers of Woman Suffrage - Early Struggles and Persecutions," 1936 Feb. 14. Speech, U.S. Congress. Printed copy and background material (Folder 7)
  - Speech, Virginia State Workers Education Conference, Norfolk, Virginia, 1936 Feb. 15. Correspondence and miscellanea (Folder 8)
  - Speech, National Farmer Labor Party, Chicago, Illinois, 1936 Mar. 6. Correspondence, flyer, schedules (Folder 9)
  - Radio broadcast, 1936 April. Correspondence (Folder 10)
  - Speech, Minneapolis Peace Demonstration, Minneapolis, Minnesota, 1936 April 25. Correspondence, flyer (Folder 11)
  - "Cooperatives in Minnesota," 1936 May 6. Speech, U.S. Congress. Printed copy, notes and clippings (Folder 12)
  - "National Union for Social Justice Program," 1938 May 8. Speech, U.S. Congress. Printed copy and typescript (Folder 13)
  - "Spanish War Veterans Legislation," 1936 May 22. Speech, U.S. Congress. Printed copy, correspondence (Folder 14)
  - "Minnesota Public Works," 1936 May 28. Speech, U.S. Congress. Printed copy and notes (Folder 15)
  - "The American Farmer," 1936 June. Speech, U.S. Congress. Proof copy, copies of bills, notes, background material (Folder 16)
  - "Fire Demon's Toll," 1936 June 3. Speech, U.S. Congress. Proof copy and background material (Box 378., Folder 1)
  - "Polish - American Contribution to Our Republic," 1936 June 3. Speech, U.S. Congress. Printed copy and notes (Folder 2)
  - "Farmer Labor Party - History, Platforms and Programs," 1936 June 17. Speech, U.S. Congress. Printed copy, notes, correspondence (Folder 3)
  - "St. Lawrence Waterway," 1936 June 18. Speech, U.S. Congress. Printed copy, notes (Folder 4)
  - Speech on radio station KSTP, 1936 Oct. 16. Typescript (Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous schedules, invitations, correspondence, notes, 1937 (Folder 6)
  - Statement on arms embargo, 1937 Mar 23. Typescript draft and two printed copies (Folder 7)
  - "Prevention of Profiteering in Time of War," Report of the Committee on Military Affairs on S. 25, 1937 May 6. Printed copy (Folder 8)
  - Speech, American Labor Party, 1937 June 11. Clippings, correspondence (Folder 9)
  - "Social Security," 1937 June 11. Typescript speech draft (Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous notes, speech drafts, background material, printed copies, correspondence, pamphlet, 1938
    - General (Folder 11)
    - Airships (Folder 12)
    - Unemployment and relief (Folder 13)
    - War debts (Folder 14)
  - Schedules and invitations, 1938. Correspondence (Box 379., Folder 1)
  - "If It Is War You Want-," War - What For, 1938. Printed copy (Folder 2)
  - "Why I Am Sending My Boy to Military School," Physical Culture, 1938 Jan. Printed copy and correspondence (Folder 3)
  - "Pledges Leading U.S. to Enter European Wars, New York Journal and American, 1938 Mar. 6. Two printed copies (Folder 4)
  - Remarks, U.S. Congress, 1938 April. Five printed copies on various subjects (Folder 5)
  - "We Are Again On the Verge of War," 1938 April 6. Speech, CBS radio. Typescript draft and printed copy (Folder 6)
  - Remarks, Swedish-American 300th Anniversary Celebration, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1938 April 8. Schedule, correspondence, pamphlets (Folder 7)
  - "Relief and Work Relief Appropriations," 1938 April 20. Speech, U.S. Congress. Two draft copies and notes (Folder 8)
  - "Keep America Out of War," 1938 April 27. Speech, U.S. Congress. Printed copy (Folder 9)
  - "Aviation - Our First Line of Defense," 1938 April 29. Speech, U.S. Congress. Printed copy, notes, correspondence (Folder 10)
  - "May Day," 1938 May 1. Speech, Washington, D.C. Flyer, typescript copy, correspondence (Folder 11)
  - "Delaware - Founding of the State," 1938 May 5. Speech, U.S. Congress. Typescript and correspondence (Folder 12)
  - "Government Ownership of Railways, 1938 May 12. Speech, U.S. Congress. Two typescript copies, correspondence (Folder 13)
  - "The Public Ownership Program in Congress," 1938 May 28 Speech, NBC radio. Printed copy, correspondence, notes (Box 380., Folder 1)
  - "Every Man Has the Divine Right to Work," 1938 June 1. Speech, U.S. Congress. Typescript, correspondence (Folder 2)
  - "Social Democratic Federation," 1938 June 7. Speech, U.S. Congress. Two printed copies, correspondence (Folder 3)
  - "We Must Not Adjourn Now," 1938 June 14. Speech, U.S. Congress. Printed copy, notes, correspondence (Folder 4)
  - "Our Foreign Policy," 1938 Sept. 30. Radio broadcast, WCCO, Minneapolis, Minnesota. Typescript, notes (Folder 5)
  - "How Big A Navy?" The Forum, 1938 Dec. Printed copy, notes, clipping (Folder 6)
  - "Neutrality," 1938 Dec. 4. Speech on CBS radio for the Harvard Guardian Conference. Typescript (Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous, 1939. Holograph and typescript drafts, pamphlet, flyer, correspondence (Folder 8)
  - Notes on the Second Deficiency Appropriation Bill, 1939. Correspondence, pamphlet, typescript (Folder 9)
  - Notes on Union Now, 1939. Printed materials, clipping (Folder 10)
  - Remarks on various subjects, U.S. Congress, 1939. Printed copies (Folder 11)
  - "Farmer Labor Party - A Political Pattern for America," 1939. Typescript speech draft (Folder 12)
  - "Social Security - The American Way," 1939 Jan 21. Radio broadcast. Typescript, notes, printed copy (Folder 13)
  - "Secret Military Conferences," 1939 Mar. 1. Remarks, U.S. Congress. Printed copy (Folder 14)
  - "Flaxseed - An Essential Crop," 1939 Mar. 2. Speech, U.S. Congress. Two printed copies, correspondence (Folder 15)
  - "The Monitor and the Merrimac," 1939 Mar. 9. Speech draft and notes (Folder 16)
  - Remarks on war debts, U.S. Congress, 1939 Mar. 16. Correspondence, resolution and petitions, typescript (Box 381., Folder 1)
  - "Works Progress Administration," 1939 April 8. Speech, U.S. Congress. Printed copy and correspondence (Folder 2)
  - "War Debts and the West Indies," 1939 April 19. Speech, U.S. Congress. Printed copy and notes (Folder 3)
  - Remarks on Hormel (Austin, Minnesota) products, U.S. Congress, 1939 May 18. Printed copy, correspondence (Folder 4)
  - "Predatory Democracies," Today's Challenge, 1939 June-July. Two printed copies (Folder 5)
  - Remarks on war debts, U.S. Congress, 1939 June 19. Notes, printed copy, pamphlet (Folder 6)
  - Speech on trade with Japan, U.S. Congress, 1939 July 28. Printed copy, correspondence (Folder 7)
  - "Thirtieth Anniversary of American Aviation," 1939 Aug.2. Speech, U.S. Congress. Draft, correspondence, printed copy (Folder 8)
  - Radio broadcast on neutrality, NBC, 1939 Sept. 2. Telegrams, typescript copy (Folder 9)
  - "Neutrality," 1939 Oct. 14. CBS radio broadcast. Typescript draft, printed copy, correspondence (Folder 10)
  - Speech on France's war debts, U.S. Congress, 1939 Oct. 14. Proof, printed copy (Folder 11)
  - Speech, John Ericsson Society, 1939 Nov. 22. Notes, programs, typescript (Folder 12)
  - "Make Europe Pay War Debts," 1939 Dec. 15. Radio broadcast. Notes, draft, typescript (Folder 13)
  - Fragments of drafts, 1940 (?) Typescripts (Box 382., Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1940. Schedules, correspondence, programs, issues of the Congressional Record. Printed copies, typescripts (Folder 2)
  - Notes on the British war debt to the United States, 1940. Typescript, pamphlet, clippings (Folder 3)
  - Speech, Sveas Soner Singing Society, Chicago, Illinois, 1940. Correspondence (Folder 4)
  - "The Right To Work," 1940 Jan. 13. Radio broadcast from a People's Lobby meeting. Notes, draft, typescript (Folder 5)
  - "Make Europe Pay War Debts," 1940 Jan. 20. Radio broadcast. Notes, clippings, correspondence (Folder 6)
  - "Government Ownership of Utilities," 1940 Jan. 23. Speech, U.S. Congress. Printed copy (Folder 7)
  - Speech notes about Hernando De Soto on the 400th anniversary of his discovery of the Mississippi River, 1940 Jan. 29. Holograph draft, clippings, corresdpondence, S.J. Res. 175 (Folder 8)
  - "George Washington's Anniversary," 1940 Feb. 22. Speech. Typescript notes and draft (Folder 9)
  - Speech, Board of Trade for German-American Commerce, Inc., honoring Duke Karl Eduard of Saxe Coburg and Gotha, New York City, New York, 1940 Mar. 20. Schedules, press releases, correspondence, clippings (Folder 10)
  - "How Members of Congress Measure Public Opinion Among Their Constituents," 1940 Mar. 30. Speech, Eastern Public Speaking Association, Washington, D.C. Two printed copies, clipping, correspondence (Folder 11)
  - "Let Television Advance," 1940 April 6. Radio broadcast. Typescript, correspondence, background material (Folder 12)
  - "America's Policy Toward Insular Possessions of Foreign Countries," 1940 April 28. Radio broadcast, American Forum of the Air. Two typescript drafts, typescript copy, correspondence (Folder 13)
  - "Let Europe Pay War Debts," Social Justice, 1940 April 29. Printed copy (Folder 14)
  - "Civil Aeronautics Authority and Air Safety Board," 1940 May 1. Speech, U.S. Congress. Printed copy, background material, clippings (Folder 15)
  - Remarks on a 'seventh column', U.S. Congress, 1940 May 24. Draft and typescript (Box 383., Folder 1)
  - "American Occupation of Greenland and Iceland," 1940 June 6. Speech, U.S. Congress. Printed copy (Folder 2)
  - "Shall the United States Sell Immediately to the Allies Any of Its Planes, Ships, and Other War Supplies," 1940 June 7. Forum of the Air broadcast
    - Typescript drafts, two printed copies, clippings (Folder 3)
    - Correspondence
      - Reactions against (Folder 4-5)
      - Reactions for (Folder 6-7)
  - "Floyd B. Olson - Pioneer of Social Progress," 1940 June 13. Speech, U.S. Congress. Printed copy (Box 384., Folder 1)
  - "Magnus Johnson - The Man and His Cause," 1940 June 30. Speech at the dedication of a memorial monument, Dassel, Minnesota. Typescript, printed copy, clippings (Folder 2)
  - "National Advertising and the Consumer," 1940 July 8. Speech, U.S. Congress. Printed copy (Folder 3)
  - "Six Men and War," 1940 July 11. Speech, U.S. Congress. Printed copies and correspondence (Folder 4)
  - Speech, Svenskarnas Dag, Minneapolis, Minnesota, 1940 July 14. Holograph notes, correspondence, clippings, pamphlets (Folder 5)
  - "Shall We Conscript American Manpower Now?" 1940 July 28. Radio broadcast, WOL Mutual Broadcasting System. Draft, background material, clippings, typescript (Folder 6)
  - Statement advocating a new national party, and reactions, 1940 July 31. Typescript, correspondence, clippings (Folder 7)
  - "Anti-Conscription," 1940 Aug. 10. Radio address, NBC. Typescript drafts, printed copy, press release, correspondence (Folder 8)
  - "Farmer Labor Party - A Political Pattern for America," 1940 Aug. 15. Speech, U.S. Congress. Printed copy (Folder 9)
  - "Shall the United States Now Seize Foreign Island Possessions in the Western Hemisphere in Payment of the War Debts," 1940 Aug 19. Statement. Typescript draft (Folder 10)
  - "Archangel and Vladivostock Expeditions," 1940 Aug. 26. Speech, U.S. Congress. Printed copy (Folder 11)
  - "Four Hundred and Fifty-One European Wars Since Columbus," 1940 Aug. 27. Speech, U.S. Congress. Printed copy (Folder 12)
- CARD FILE, n.d.
  - Alphabetical files of names of voters hostile to Ernest Lundeen, names of campaign workers and volunteers, one unidentified list and one unsorted list (Box 385.)
  - Alphabetical file of names of individuals, organizations, businesses, etc. are a personal and professional cash account; one unidentified, unsorted list (Box 386.)
  - Alphabetical file of names of individuals and businesses involved in lawsuits handled by the Lundeen law firm (Box 387.)
  - Alphabetical file of names of political supporters, and one alphabetical file of names arranged by state (Box 388.)
  - Alphabetical file of names of Minnesota cities and political supporters in each; some cards unsorted (Box 389.)
  - Two unidentified files of names; one file of names of subscribers to Uncle Sam (Box 390.)
  - Alphabetical file of names of military personnel known to Ernest Lundeen; a list of dates to remember; a file of mottoes and sayings (Box 391.)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS, 1916-1940
  - Political campaign posters, flyers, two scrapbooks of clippings about elections and candidates, sample campaign buttons, Lundeen's 1916 election return certificate (Box 392.)
  - Poster advertising a mass meeting appearance by Congressman Lundeen, pencil sketch of Charles A. Lindberg, medal inscribed "For Kultur," one photo-plaque, six convention badges, scrapbook with clippings about Congressional personalities, two copies of a poem, "The Redwoods," Rollo Mudge's posthumous tribute to Lundeen (Box 393.)
- MISCELLANY, n.d.
  - Checkbooks, check stubs, bank statements, bills and receipts (Box 394.)
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1860-1940
  - 102 prints depicting Lundeen, his brothers and sisters and their families, 1860-1938 (Folder A-D)
  - 139 prints depicting friends of the Reverend and Mrs. Charles H. Lundin, some with identifying descriptions and dates written by Ernest Lundeen, 1872-1896 (Folder E-mI)
  - 3 prints and 10 post cards depicting Lundeen, his teachers and classmates in the Beresford District School near Brooklyn, South Dakota; a list of the students pictured; scenes of Beresford, 1889-1913 (Folder J)
  - 280 prints depicting Lundeen; Lundeen's parents, Reverend and Mrs. Charles H. Lundin; Lundeen's wife, Norma Ward Lundeen and their children Ernest Ward and Joan Jessie, 1890(?)-1942 (Folder K-mP)
  - 11 prints depicting Lundeen and his high school classmates at graduation, and at their 20th reunion; scenes of Dayton, Iowa, 1894-1938 (Folder Q)
  - 98 prints, 15 duplicates, 2 newspaper mats and one newspaper cut depicting Ernest Lundeen only, 1895(?)-1939 (Folder R-mU)
  - 77 prints and 2 duplicates depicting Lundeen, fellow students and some faculty members of Carleton College, Northfield, Minnesota, 1896-1901 (Folder V-W)
  - 105 prints and one negative depicting Lundeen's service in the Minnesota National Guard, 1898-1921 (Folder X-mAA)
  - 24 prints depicting Lundeen, Trafford Jayne and David Lundeen in their law office, and members of the Minneapolis, Minnesota Bench and Bar, 1903-1922, 1912 (Folder BB)
  - 61 prints and 2 duplicates depicting Ernest Lundeen, friends and acquaintances, 1904-1937 (Folder CC)
  - 17 prints and 2 duplicates depicting Ernest Lundeen and other legislators in the Minnesota State Legislature, 1910-1914 (Folder DD)
  - 58 prints depicting Lundeen, Mrs. Lundeen, and others on Congressional trips to Alaska, Hawaii, a U.S. military base, and Europe, 1917, 1937 (Folder EE)
  - 1 album, Congressional Party in Hawaii, 1917; 21 pages of an album of pictures depicting a Congressional trip to Hawaii, 1937 (Folder fFF)
  - 99 prints and 2 post cards depicting Lundeen during his years in Congress, including 1 inscribed photograph of Hugo Black and one of Robert La Follette, 1917-1940 (Folder GG-mII)
  - 29 prints and 3 negatives depicting aspects of Lundeen's political campaigns, 1922-1936 (Folder JJ)
  - 17 prints of political leaders including U.S. Senators Robert R. Reynolds and Robert La Follette and Minnesota Governor J. A. A. Burnquist, 1924-1939 (Folder KK)
  - 31 prints, 46 post cards and 2 negatives of Lundeen's trip to the Soviet Union with the American Rank and File Trade Union Delegation depicting the Antoshkim Club in Kharkov, parades, reform schools, scenes of Moscow, 1927-1928 (Folder LL-mMM)
  - 1 album, To Comrades and Brothers From the Workers and Peasants of the Soviet Union on the 10-th Anniversary of the October Revolution, depicting Russian leaders, buildings, classes, and the military, 1927 (Folder fNN)
  - 110 prints depicting the Bonus Expeditionary Forces and the Bonus Marchers from various states meeting, camping, marching in Washington, D.C., 1932-1934 (Folder OO-PP)
  - 93 prints of Lundeen's visit to Trujillo City, Santo Domingo, 1938 (Folder QQ)
  - 9 unidentified and/or undated prints (Folder RR)